<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header$ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/desktop/gnome/howtos/gnome-3.0-upgrade.xml" lang="en">
<title>GNOME 3.0 Upgrade Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tetromino@gmail.com">Alexandre Rostovtsev</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This is a guide for upgrading from GNOME 2.32.x to GNOME 3.0.x
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>2011-07-30</date>

<chapter>
<title>Changes</title>

<section>
<title>General changes</title>
<body>

<p>
Please see the <uri link="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.0/">GNOME
3.0 Release Notes</uri> for what is new in this major release of GNOME.
</p>

<p>
Briefly: GNOME 3.0 includes two desktop modes&mdash;standard and fallback.
Fallback mode uses <c>gnome-base/gnome-panel</c> and <c>x11-wm/metacity</c>, and
is similar in appearance and behavior to GNOME 2. Standard mode uses
<c>gnome-base/gnome-shell</c> and <c>x11-wm/mutter</c>, and looks and behaves
<e>completely</e> differently from previous GNOME releases. By default, the
choice of desktop mode is determined by the system's graphics hardware and
drivers (standard mode requires modern 3D graphics capabilities).
</p>

<p>There is a <uri link="https://live.gnome.org/GnomeShell/Tour">quick
tour</uri> of standard mode's GNOME Shell available on the GNOME website.
For an in-depth guide to using GNOME Shell, see
<uri link="https://live.gnome.org/GnomeShell/CheatSheet">the GNOME Shell
cheat sheet</uri>. GNOME Shell at first may feel alien and limited to an
experienced GNOME 2 user. We strongly encourage users to persist and make
themselves use it for a few days; those who take the time to get used to GNOME
Shell's behavior usually grow to love it and don't want to go back to an
old-fashioned GNOME 2-like desktop environment.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Languages and encodings</title>
<body>

<p>
GNOME 3.0 obtains user language settings from <c>sys-apps/accountsservice</c>.
The language can be set in GNOME from the <e>My Account</e> entry in the upper
right corner menu. Alternatively, you can directly edit accountsservice user
files. For example, to have user <c>jrandom</c> use British English, you can 
(as root) edit <path>/var/lib/AccountsService/users/jrandom</path> so it reads
the following:
</p>
<pre>
[User]
Language=en_GB.utf8
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Fonts</title>
<body>

<p>
GNOME 3.0 uses <c>media-fonts/cantarell</c> as its default font. Unfortunately,
Cantarell only includes a subset of the extended Latin alphabet. Users of
languages whose writing systems are not covered by Cantarell will probably want
to switch to another font, such as <c>media-fonts/dejavu</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Set DejaVu (size 10) as the default font">
$ <i>gsettings set org.gnome.desktop.interface font-name 'DejaVu Sans 10'</i>
$ <i>gsettings set org.gnome.desktop.interface document-font-name 'DejaVu Sans 10'</i>
$ <i>gconftool-2 -s -t string /apps/metacity/general/titlebar_font 'DejaVu Sans Bold 10'</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Applets <e>(FIXME add a gnome-applets snapshot)</e></title>
<body>
<p>
GNOME 2 applets cannot be used in GNOME 3.0. Fallback mode allows applets,
although most have not yet been ported to the new, gtk3-based APIs. In
standard mode, there are no applets at all. Some traditional applet
functionality can be replicated using third-party GNOME Shell extensions.
</p>
<p>
In order to manage gnome-panel settings (either add/remove or rearrange
applet positions) one has to hold down the <c>Alt</c> key when clicking
on the panel. This opens relevant menu for changing either panel or applet
settings.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Shut down and reboot <e>(FIXME: fix bug 377107 to allow GNOME_SHELL_EXTENSIONS)</e> </title>
<body>
<p>
GNOME Shell developers made a <uri
link="https://live.gnome.org/GnomeShell/Design/Whiteboards/SystemStopRestart">controversial
decision</uri> to not show any sort of shut down or power off menu by default.
The <em>Power Off</em> menu item becomes visible after clicking on the upper
right corner menu and holding down the <c>Alt</c> key.
</p>

<p>
If you need an easily discoverable GUI for shutting down the machine (for
example, if deploying GNOME 3.0 in a corporate environment where users are
required to turn off their computers at the end of the day), you can install the
alternative-status-menu extension. To do so, add
<c>GNOME_SHELL_EXTENSIONS="alternative-status-menu"</c> to your
<c>/etc/make.conf</c>, and emerge <c>gnome-extra/gnome-shell-extensions</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Icons on the desktop</title>
<body>

<p>
In GNOME 3.0, Nautilus by default no longer manages the desktop, and the
<path>~/Desktop</path> folder is simply treated as a normal folder with files.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Compiz</title>
<body>

<p>
GNOME 3.0 standard mode (i.e. GNOME Shell) is incompatible with Compiz.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>General configurability and extensions</title>
<body>

<p>
GNOME 3.0 is designed to appear significantly less configurable than GNOME 2.
For example, by default there is no easily discoverable GUI for changing the
Gtk+ theme. Many configuration settings are hidden, but can still be changed
from gsettings (dconf), gconf, or using the <c>gnome-extra/gnome-tweak-tool</c>
GUI. Discussion of such hidden settings is outside the scope of this guide.
</p>

<p>
GNOME Shell's behavior can be significantly altered using <uri
link="https://live.gnome.org/GnomeShell/Extensions">extensions</uri>. Gentoo
packages the extensions from the official GNOME repository as
<c>gnome-extra/gnome-shell-extensions</c>; there are also numerous third-party
developers publishing extensions on various websites.
</p>

<impo>
By default, GNOME Shell loads all installed extensions. However, extension code
quality is highly variable, and some extensions can render GNOME completely
unusable. Gentoo cannot offer support for problems caused by third-party
extensions.
</impo>

<p>
Extensions can be disabled on a per-user basis (e.g. if a user does not want
to load a particular extension installed systemwide) using gsettings:
</p>
<pre caption="Disabling dock and xrandr-indicator extensions">
$ <i>gsettings set org.gnome.shell disabled-extensions '["dock", "xrandr-indicator"]'</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>

<section>
<title>GDM freezes after the password has been entered</title>

<body>
<p>
As reported in <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=375615">bug
#375615</uri>, for some people certain versions of
<c>x11-drives/nvidia-drivers</c> cause some Gtk+ applications to crash; one
effect of this is to break login using GDM. Until the problem is fixed, try
using a different version of <c>nvidia-drivers</c>; 275.09.07 is believed to
work well.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>GNOME starts in fallback mode</title>
<body>

<p>
GNOME will start in fallback mode if it detects that the graphics hardware and
drivers are insufficiently capable. To see a more detailed explanation of why
GNOME does not start in standard mode, run
<path>/usr/libexec/gnome-session-check-accelerated-helper</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Sample gnome-session-check-accelerated-helper output">
$ <i>/usr/libexec/gnome-session-check-accelerated-helper</i>
gnome-session-is-accelerated: No hardware 3D support.
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>GNOME starts in standard mode</title>
<body>

<p>
To force GNOME to start in fallback mode (e.g. due to poor performance or
personal taste), open System Settings (or <path>gnome-control-center</path>
from the terminal), go to <e>System Info &rarr; Graphics</e>, and turn on
<e>Forced Fallback Mode</e>. Alternatively, from a terminal:
</p>

<pre caption="Force GNOME to start in fallback mode">
$ <i>gsettings set org.gnome.desktop.session session-name gnome-fallback</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Epiphany and Adobe Flash</title>
<body>

<p>
Out of the box, Epiphany 3 cannot load <c>www-plugins/adobe-flash</c> because
the browser links to Gtk+-3 while the plugin links to Gtk+-2. On amd64, there
is a workaround: if you emerge <c>adobe-flash</c> with <c>USE=-64bit</c>, the
plugin will be called through <c>www-plugins/nspluginwrapper</c>, avoiding
incompatibility between Gtk+ versions. On x86, unfortunately there is no good
workaround at this time; we suggest using a gtk2-based browser (such as
<c>www-clients/firefox</c> or <c>www-clients/chromium</c>).
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
